Animation Number 1
My work was perfect.
I'm quite confident I can say that.
Animation Number 1
Knowing that any blunder could easily spell the end,
I ascended the steps to this shrine,
Animation Number 1
and for this very day
I took utmost precautions.
Animation Number 1
And yet
（貝木(かいき)）
千石撫子(せんごくなでこ)が こうも あっさりと
Sengoku Nadeko so easily saw through my lies...
俺のウソを看破したのは
そもそも こいつは俺のことなんて
...because she never trusted me one bit to begin with.
まるっきり
信用していなかったということだ
So there was nothing to deceive in the first place.
だから
だますもなにもなかったのだ
With that in mind,
Animation Number 14
you could say I was deceived by her.
But no
Animation Number 14
I should have put more emphasis on the problems of her heart.
俺は もっと
心の問題を重視すべきだったのだ
I didn't think that this girl had closed her heart to this extent.
ここまで この娘が
心を閉ざしていたとは思わなかった
It wasn't a shadow within a soul. It was a soul made of shadows.
心の闇ではなく 闇の心だった
She snubs everyone.
誰のことも相手にしていない
For an entire month
Animation Number 14
I was convinced I could create some amount of trust
with Cat's Cradle, donations, and sake.
Animation Number 14
I thought I'd won Sengoku Nadeko's trust.
I was nothing but an enormous fool.
Animation Number 14
Really now, you liar...
（千石）本当 もうウソつき
Everyone... Everyone really does nothing but lie.
みんな みんな本当に
ウソばっかり
North
Shira
hebi
Shrine
（貝木）う…
（千石）ウフッ
Beautiful.
（貝木）美しい
So
Animation Number 49
I thought.
Hitagi End          Part Six
Font used in the video: HGP Mincho B
Really, so full of lies.
（千石）本当にウソばっかり
本当にウソばっかり
Really, so full of lies!
In the world, this universe, this world...
世の中って 世界って この世って
Really, really, really, really, really, really...
本当に 本当に 本当に
Lies, lies, lies, lies, full of lies!
ウソ ウソ ウソ ウソ ウソ
ばっかりなんだから
You really are a liar!
本当に もう ウソつきなんだから
Hah, who do you think you're talking to? And what are you talking about?
（貝木）は？　誰に言っている？
そして 何を言っている？
You make it sound like you've never told one lie in your entire life.
まるで 自分はウソをついたことが
１度もないかのような言いぐさだな
But you've been deceiving everyone around you this whole time.
お前だって
周囲の全てを だましてきたくせに
If I'm a liar, you're the bigger one.
Animation Number 70
It's impossible for you to grant the wishes of someone else.
（貝木）
お前には 誰かの願いを
かなえることなんか できないよ
You only think of yourself.
Animation Number 83
You only trust yourself.
Did "becoming a god" give you the false idea that you are someone special?
お前 神様になったからって
自分のことを 特別な存在だとでも
勘違いしているんじゃないのか？
Pink Scene
Animation Number 'none'
She said she hated me.
Pink Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（千石）
嫌いだって言われたんだ
Pink Scene
Animation Number 'none'
It's like I didn't say anything at all.
Animation Number 90
She lives in her own world.
She said she hated "cute brats" like me.
（千石）
私みたいな かわいいガキは
嫌いだって言われたんだ
Let's see... Who said that...
えっと
誰に言われたんだったっけな
Who was it... Was it Koyomi-oniichan?
誰だっけな
暦(こよみ)おにいちゃんだったっけな
It was Senjougahara.
Animation Number 94
I just know.
But about that... What should I do?
だけど それって
どうすればいいのかな？
It's true that I'm a "cute brat," but is any part of that really my fault?
私は確かに かわいいガキだけれど
けど それって基本的に
私のせいじゃないじゃない？
I hate being like this as well.
私だって こんな自分は嫌いだよ
But this is who I am... This is me, so I can't do anything about it.
だけど これが自分なんだから
これが 私なんだから
しかたないじゃない
But still... Even if I feel like that, it's who I am.
それでも
そんな自分でも
自分なんだから
So I have to love myself.
好きになるしかないじゃない
I have to love myself, who I hate so much.
大嫌いな自分でも愛せるような
I need to become like a god, so that I can love myself no matter how I am.
どんな自分でも愛せるような
神様みたいな自分に
なるしかないじゃない
That's...
（貝木）そう… おっ
That's not true.
そうじゃないな
In the end, even now, even after becoming a god...
結局 お前は 今に至っても まだ
神様になっても まだ
Just like before... Just like back when you were human...
昔と同じように
人間だったころと同じように
...your environment swings you around every which way.
周囲に いいように
振り回されているだけなんだよ
Just like how everyone praised you like "cute, cute," they just praise you like "god, god."
かわいい かわいいと
もてはやされているように
神様 神様と
もてはやされているだけなんだ
You're nothing but a doll, past and present.
お前が お人形さんなのは
今も昔も ちっとも変わらねえよ
That's where some woman I knew was different.
そういうところ
俺の知っている女は違ったぜ
She refused an offer for a god to save her.
あいつは 神様に救われることを
拒否したぜ
She rejected taking it easy and being happy.
楽になることを 幸せになることを
拒絶したぜ
I had thought that staying that way would be better for her.
俺はな
あいつは そのままのほうがいい
と思っていた
But she persistently chose a way of life that didn't rely on gods. That's what she wished for.
なのに あいつは あくまで
神に頼らない生き方を選んだんだ
願ったんだ
The outcome, the result of first contact, someone's or something's fault...
成り行きとか 出会い頭とか
誰かのせいとか 何かのせいとか
She denied everything that put her at ease.
そういう 心地良さそうなのを
全部 否定してきた
After all the thought I put into her, she repaid the kindness with resentment.
いろいろ 気を回してやった俺を
逆恨みする ありさまだぜ
Hey, aren't you and her totally different?
なあ お前とは 大違いだろう？
They'd never synch.
Animation Number 121
You're right. That's totally different.
（千石）そうだね 大違いかもね
Though I don't know who you're talking about and with what feelings.
誰のことを どんな気持ちで
語っているのか分からないけれど
But...
でもさ
But the reality is it's someone's fault, isn't it?
それでも 現実問題
誰かのせいってことは
あるでしょう？
Whether it's something right off the bat or something I stumbled upon...
出会い頭にしても
行き当たりばったりにしても
私の場合
...in my case, it's an absolute that it's Ougi's fault.
扇(おうぎ)さんのせいってのが
絶対にあるわけだし
Ougi?
扇？
Hold on.
Animation Number 130
What?
Is that a name?
Animation Number 130
Come to think of it, there was something I didn't understand.
（貝木）
そういえば
分からないことがあった
How did she know the location of "the essence of god" that Gaen-senpai loaned, or rather entrusted with Araragi?
どうして彼女が
阿良々木(あららぎ)が
臥煙(がえん)先輩から預けられていた
託されていた
神様のもとの在りかを
知っていたのだろう？
Can it be that there was someone who encouraged her to look somewhere?
まさか それを促した誰かが
いたというのか？
Someone who set Sengoku Nadeko up to become a god?
千石撫子を神様に仕立てあげた
誰かが
So, you're trying to deceive me too?
Animation Number 137
Kaiki-san "as well."
貝木さんも…
That means there was someone that tried to deceive Nadeko sometime, somewhere.
ならば ほかにも
千石撫子を だまそうとした 誰かが
いつかどこかに いたということだ
The person who deceived Sengoku Nadeko, instead of saying she was cute, encouraged her to become a god...
千石撫子を だまし
かわいがらずに
神様に仕立てあげた 誰かは
扇？
Was that Ougi?
Ougi?
Animation Number 140
（貝木）うっ あ… ぐふっ
Well... In the end, it doesn't matter.
（千石）
まあ どうでもいいんだけど
No, wait, it does matter. I can't do anything to resist myself.
いや どうでもよくはないか
抵抗するのは しかたないけれど
But, Koyomi-oniichan, it's not nice to try to deceive me.
でも 暦おにいちゃん
私を だまそうとしたのは
よくないよね？
It's not nice to lie to me.
私にウソをついたのは
よくないよね？
Araragi really has nothing to do with my actions.
（貝木）
阿良々木は別に
俺の行動とは関係がねえぜ
Oh! This calls for a penalty.
（千石）
あ！　これはペナルティだよね？
I'll keep my promise. I'll wait until your graduation.
約束は守る
卒業式までは待ってあげる
But I'll kill a few more. I'll kill a few more as your punishment.
でも もう少し殺そう
罰として もう少し殺そう
And
Animation Number 151
I'll slaughter
his five or so
Animation Number 151
friends and family.
Right in front of Koyomi-oniichan's eyes!
暦おにいちゃんの目の前で
Of course, Tsukihi-chan and Karen-san are a given.
やっぱり 月火(つきひ)ちゃんと
火憐(かれん)さんは鉄板かなあ
And Hanekawa-san...
あとは羽川(はねかわ)さん
それに 会ったことはないけど
Also, though I've never met her, doesn't Koyomi-oniichan have a best friend named Hachikuji Mayoi-chan?
暦おにいちゃんが
一番 仲が良い友達だっていう
八九寺真宵(はちくじまよい)ちゃん？
And I kind of don't want to... I really don't want to, but Kanbaru-san too, I suppose.
そして これもちょっと やだけど
すごく やだけど 神原(かんばる)さんかなあ
Sengoku, you said that you didn't want to become a god, right?
千石
お前 神様になんか なりたかった
わけじゃないって言ったよな？
I did. Why?
（千石）言ったけど？
You said you became one against your wishes...
（貝木）
なりたくて
なったわけじゃないって
（千石）言ったよ
I did say that. What's wrong with that?
それが どうかした？
Then do you want to become a manga artist?
（貝木）じゃあ お前
漫画家になりたいのか？
Animation Number 149
わあ〜 あっあ あ〜！
わあっ あ…
う… わあ〜！
（千石）わああ〜！
（貝木）う…
ああ… なんで知ってる
なんで知ってる なんで知ってる…
Why do you know! Why do you know! Why do you know! Why do you know!
さ… さては！
It can't be!
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
You peeked!
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
見たな！
You peeked! You peeked! You peeked! You peeked! You peeked!
見たな 見たな 見たな 見たな〜！
Yeah, I took a look. I peeked in.
（貝木）ああ 見たぜ 見たんだ
By twisting the lock open with a 10 yen coin.
10円玉で くるっと回して
鍵を開けてな
Money really is a valuable thing.
お金ってなあ
やっぱ 大切だよなあ
I-I said that nobody should ever open that door!
ぜ… 絶対に
開けちゃダメって言ったのに
I didn't even want Koyomi-oniichan to see!
暦おにいちゃんにだって
見られたくなかったのに〜！
You're good at drawing.
うまいじゃねえか 絵
Furthermore, the plot was just amazing...
しかも その内容が すごいって
What was with that melt-your-brain opportunistic romantic comedy?
なんだよ あの
とろけるような
ご都合主義のラブコメは
Is it something from the 80s? You think a guy like that exists in real life? So absurd.
80年代かよ
あんな男が現実にいるかよ
バカバカしい
And the plot was pretty perverted, you know.
しかも 展開的には
結構エッチだったりしてな
The character reference guide was pretty thick and overwhelming too.
（貝木）
設定資料集も かなりの分厚さで
圧倒されたぜ
But you tried to cram in too many settings.
しかしまあ 設定 盛り過ぎだろ
Smarten them up a bit, and they'll suit everyone better.
あれは
もうちょっとスマートにしたほうが
万人受けすると思うぜ 俺は
K-Kill!
こ… 殺す！
Kill! Kill! Kill! I'll kill you and then kill myself!
殺す 殺す 殺す
お前を殺して 私も死ぬ！
Kill, huh?
Animation Number 248
So you finally
give me the time of day.
Animation Number 248
It's useless to kill me.
俺を殺してもムダだぜ
You never really thought about it?
考えてはみなかったのか？
Even the parents that are just doting on you...
いくらお前を猫かわいがりしている
お前の親だって
...will open that closet someday if you continue to be missing.
行方不明が続けば
いずれは
あのクローゼットを開けるぜ
But, if you stop being a god now, become a human, and go back to your room...
ま… でも
今すぐ神様をやめて 人間に戻り
部屋に戻れば
...you can destroy them all with your own hands with no issues, right?
問題なく 自分の手で
処分できるんじゃないのか？
If someone else seeing them is so embarrassing, then...
見られるのが
そんなに恥ずかしいんだったら…
Enough! I can't stop being a god for some foolish reason like that!
ふざけんな！
そんな バカみたいな理由で
神様を やめられるわけないだろ！
"A reason like that," huh?
そんな理由で… ね
Then, let me ask you... What kind of reason would it take for you to stop being a god?
じゃあ お前
どんな理由なら
神様を やめられるんだ？
No matter who I talked to...
誰に話を聞いてもよ
I talked to Senjougahara, to Hanekawa, I even talked to your parents...
戦場ヶ原(せんじょうがはら)から聞いても
羽川から聞いても
両親から話を聞いてさえ
None of them knew that you had a hobby of that sort.
お前が あんな趣味を
持っているだなんて情報はなかった
You obstinately hid those embarrassing creations from everyone.
そこまで お前は かたくなに
あれらの恥ずかしい創作物を
隠しきったんだ
You didn't tell anyone.
お前は 誰にも言わなかった
In other words, you did that because you consider it to be your true dream, right?
それは つまり
お前にとって
それが本当の夢だからだろ？
Dream
Animation Number 274
Your real wish isn't something you tell others. Not even to god.
本当の願い事は
他人にも神様にも
言うもんじゃないからな
You must be happy now that you're a god. You must be having fun.
神様になった お前は
幸せなんだろう
楽しいんだろう
But it's not that you wanted to become a god, right?
だけど お前
神様になりたかったわけじゃ
ないんだろう？
You're so bored that you engross yourself in cat's cradle while waiting a mere six months, you know?
たった半年待つだけのことで
あや取りに熱中してしまえるほど
暇を持て余しているんだぞ？
After you kill Araragi and the others, what the hell are you going to do?
阿良々木たちを殺したあと
一体 どうするつもりなんだ？
No matter how happy you are, you're only a gatekeeper who will watch things rot away.
どれだけ幸せだろうと
朽ちるのを見守る
番人でしかないぞ お前は
You drew an unlucky lot.
貧乏くじだ
It's not like you wanted to become a god. Not like you wanted to become happy.
（貝木）
お前は 神様になりたいわけでも
幸せになりたいわけでもなかった
You wanted to become a manga artist, right? Then why don't you become one?
漫画家になりたかったんだろう？
だったら なんでならないんだ？
ハア ハア ハア…
A-Are you an idiot? Those are just scribbles.
バ… バカじゃないの？
あんなの ただの落書きだよ
I didn't want people to see those unskillful, embarrassing drawings.
つたなくて 恥ずかしいから
見られたくなかっただけだよ
My dream? Don't tell me such foolish things!
夢だなんて
バカバカしいこと言わないでよ！
They're all trash!
あんなの ごみだよ
I wanted to throw them out, but I was too embarrassed. Of course that's the reason I hid them there!
捨てたいけど
捨てるのも恥ずかしいから
あそこに隠していただけに
決まってるじゃない！
Don't talk about what you created like that, Sengoku.
自分で作ったものを
そんなふうに言うもんじゃないぞ
千石
Creation is an embarrassing process, and dreams are embarrassing as well.
（貝木）
創作は恥ずかしいものだし
それに 夢も恥ずかしいものだ
You can't help that. That's something very common.
それは しかたがない
当たり前のことだ
But, at least, it's not something that you should belittle yourself over.
だが 少なくとも そんなふうに
自分で
卑下していいものじゃないんだぞ
Besides, they were pretty good. Maybe you have that thing called talent.
（貝木）
それに うまかったじゃないか
才能ってやつが
あるんじゃないのか？　お前
There's no way that I do. Besides, I can't become one just by thinking I can be one, right?
（千石）そんなわけないじゃない
それに なろうと思って
なれるものじゃないでしょ
But if you don't think about becoming one, you'll never become one.
（貝木）
だが なろうと思わなきゃ
なれないものだぜ
Unlike becoming a god or a happy person.
神様とか 幸せとかと違って
Besides, that's something you can't become if you're a god.
それに 神様では なれないものだ
You have to be human.
人間じゃなければ
Sengoku, I like money.
千石 俺は金が好きだ
I'll tell you why. It's because money can take the place of everything.
なぜかといえば
金は全ての代わりになるからだ
You can buy things. You can buy lives.
物も買える 命も買える
You can buy people. You can buy hearts.
人も買える 心も買える
Sold Out
New Product
Dreams
Happiness
Love
You can buy happiness. You can buy dreams.
（貝木）
幸せも買える 夢も買える
500th Lottery
National Autonomous Lottery
Group 00
Sold at   Prefectures and Cities
Trustee   Bank of All That Is Fake
Make your dreams come true with the lottery!
The number below is not your lottery number
700522260685
It's very precious, but on top of that, it's not something that is irreplaceable. That's why I like it.
とても大切なもので
そして そのうえで
かけがえのないものではないから
好きだ
Conversely, I hate irreplaceable things.
逆に言うと 俺はな
かけがえのないものが 嫌いだ
"I can't live without this." Or "That is the reason why I'm alive."
これがなきゃ生きていけないとか
あれだけが生きる理由だとか
それこそは
自分の生まれてきた目的だとか
Or "That is the purpose for which I was born."
Scarcity value pisses me off to no end.
そういう希少価値に
腹が立ってしかたがない
Would you become worthless if Araragi dumped you?
阿良々木に振られたら
お前に価値はなくなるのか？
Was that the only thing you wanted to become?
お前のやりたいことは
それだけだったのか？
Is that all your life meant to you?
お前の人生は
それだけだったのか？
You know what, Sengoku?
あのな 千石
Some idiot out there is volunteering to do something as sluggish as dating Araragi for you.
（貝木）
阿良々木と つきあうなんて
かったるいことは
代わりに どっかのバカが
やってくれるってよ
So you can put an end to something that sluggish and do some other sluggish thing.
だから お前は
そんな かったるいことは
終わりにして
ほかの かったるいことを
やればいい
You have all sorts of other things you want to try, or to do, right?
やりたいことも したいことも
ほかに いくらでもあるだろ？
You had some, right? Am I wrong?
あっただろ？
違うか？
Something I want to try... Something I want to do...
（千石）
やりたいこと したいこと？
Come on, Sengoku.
（貝木）
なあ 千石
お前にとって
阿良々木以外のことは
For you, was everything in this world outside of Araragi so worthless that you didn't care at all?
どうでもいい
くだらないことだったのか？
Your parents... You didn't love those ordinary law-abiding citizens at all?
両親の…
あの善良な一般市民のことは
好きじゃなかったのか？
In your priorities list, was everything other than Araragi all trash?
お前の中の優先順位で
阿良々木以外は 全部ごみか？
They weren't...
違うよ
Then why? Why is Araragi the only one to get special treatment?
（貝木）
ならば どうしてだ？
どうして 阿良々木だけが
特別扱いになる？
Is he your alter ego or something?
あいつは
お前の分身か何かなのか？
What would you know, Kaiki-san!
貝木さんに 何が分かるの？
You don't know anything about me, Kaiki-san.
（千石）
貝木さんは 私のことなんか
何も知らないでしょう
I did all sorts of research. But that's right. I don't know anything.
（貝木）いろいろ調べた
だが そうだ
何も知らない
I know nothing important.
重要なことは 何も知らない
Because only you know about you.
お前のことは
お前しか知らないんだから
That's why you're the only person who can take care of you.
だから お前のことは
お前しか 大切にできないんだぜ
And you are the only one who can grant your dream.
そして お前の夢も
お前にしか かなえられない
Are humans allowed to randomly swap around like that?
（千石）
そんな とっかえひっかえみたいな
Liverpool
Tokyo
Holland
Greece
California
America
Switzerland
Maryland
Australia
Like, "Since that's bad, let's go with this?"
あれがダメなら
これでいこうみたいな
適当なこと してもいいの？
人間は
You can. Because you're human.
（貝木）
いいんだよ 人間なんだから
Nothing is irreplaceable. There is nothing that can't be substituted.
かけがえのない
代わりのないものなんかない
A woman I know...
（貝木）
俺の知ってる女はな
A woman I know well always treats her current romance as if it's her first.
俺の よく知っている女はな
今している恋が
常に初恋だって感じだぜ
She always looks like she's never fallen in love with someone before.
本当に人を好きになったのは
今が初めてって感じだぜ
And that's the right way to go. That's how it should be.
そして それで正しい
そうでなくっちゃダメだ
There is no peerless person. There is nothing irreplaceable.
唯一の人間なんて
かけがえのない事柄なんてない
Because humans, as humans, can redo something as much as they want.
人間は 人間だから
いくらでも やり直せる
Re-purchase anything as much as they want.
いくらでも買い直せる
For now...
とりあえず…
Use the money I gave you to go buy professional art tools or something.
俺が くれてやった金で
（貝木）
本格的な画材でも買いに行けよ
I'm telling you... I never really thought about becoming a manga artist. Not even once.
（千石）だから 私 別に
漫画家になりたいなんて思ったこと
１度もないって
And it's true that I didn't want to be one when I became one...
それに 確かに なりたくて
なったわけじゃないけれど
...but I think it would be a waste to toss aside being a god, since I had the fortune of becoming one.
せっかく 神様になれた幸運を
蹴っちゃうのも
もったいないって 普通に思うよ
But...
でも
There were people who were called gods of manga, right?
漫画を描いて
神様って呼ばれた人もいたよね
If I feel it's a waste, I can become one of those, right?
もったいないと思うなら
そうなればいいんだよね
Yeah. I'm sure you can be one.
ああ お前なら きっとなれるさ
Pretend that you were deceived and try it out as a challenge.
だまされたと思って
チャレンジしてみな
All right. I'll let you deceive me.
分かった
だまされてあげる
Oh, you...
（貝木）こいつめ
That said,
Animation Number 375
although the plan didn't quite work out as expected,
I accomplished the task given to me by Senjougahara Hitagi.
Animation Number 375
Animation Number 376
White Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Sengoku...
White Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（阿良々木）
千石
White Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Kaiki?
（阿良々木）貝木？
Kaiki! You! Why are you here?
貝木！　お前 どうしてここに？
What did you do to Sengoku?
千石に何をした！
I was asked by Gaen-senpai.
（貝木）臥煙先輩に頼まれてな
I was exorcising this girl just now.
この娘を除霊していたところだ
This job wasn't one for a con artist, but for a ghost-buster.
今回は 詐欺師としてではなく
ゴーストバスターとしての仕事
というわけさ
Coming to this town was against the rules, but since I'm not here as a con artist, it's fine, right?
この町に来たのは ルール違反だが
しかし 詐欺師としてじゃないから
いいだろう？
Of course I came to deceive, it's how I live and breathe.
Animation Number 390
Well, outside of the last five minutes just now.
Gaen-san...
（阿良々木）臥煙さんが…
B-But... What in the world did you do to Sengoku?
で… でも
千石に 一体 何をしたんだよ？
お前
The same thing I did to your little sister.
（貝木）
お前の妹にしたのと同じことだ
The same thing you did to Karen-chan?
（阿良々木）
火憐ちゃんにしたのと同じ？
Right. But this time it's not a bee.
（貝木）
そう もっとも
今回は蜂じゃあないがな
For Sengoku... For Sengoku Nadeko, it was a slug.
千石…
千石撫子の場合は
A Slug Tofu.
蛞蝓(なめくじ)だ
Though both are terrestrial molluscs,
unlike snails, slugs are often
considered stereotypically disgusting
Animation Number 394
Slug
Though both are terrestrial molluscs,
unlike snails, slugs are often
considered stereotypically disgusting
Animation Number 394
Slug
Though both are terrestrial molluscs,
unlike snails, slugs are often
considered stereotypically disgusting
Animation Number 394
Slug
Though both are terrestrial molluscs,
unlike snails, slugs are often
considered stereotypically disgusting
Animation Number 394
Slug
Though both are terrestrial molluscs,
unlike snails, slugs are often
considered stereotypically disgusting
Animation Number 394
Slug
Though both are terrestrial molluscs,
unlike snails, slugs are often
considered stereotypically disgusting
Animation Number 394
Slug
Though both are terrestrial molluscs,
unlike snails, slugs are often
considered stereotypically disgusting
Animation Number 394
Slug
Though both are terrestrial molluscs,
unlike snails, slugs are often
considered stereotypically disgusting
Animation Number 394
Slug
Of course, it's not so strong an apparition that it can seal away a snake god.
蛞蝓豆腐(どうふ)
もっとも 蛇神(へびがみ)を封じられるほど
強力な怪異ではない
As always, it's a fabricated, fake apparition.
相変わらずの でっち上げられた
偽物の怪異だからな
If Sengoku Nadeko herself hadn't been accepting the slippery lifestyle of a slug...
千石撫子自身に
ぬらりと生きる蛞蝓を
受け入れる気持ちがなければ
...I would've had no chance.
こうも拮抗はしなかった
Been accepting...
（阿良々木）
受け入れる気持ち… て 貝木！
Wait, Kaiki, what did you say to Sengoku?
お前 千石に…
何を言ったんだ？
I said the obvious.
当たり前のことさ
I told her the obvious.
（貝木）
当たり前のことを言ったんだ
Romance isn't everything. There is fun in life.
恋愛だけが全てじゃないとか
ほかにも楽しみはあるとか
Don't throw your future away. Everyone has had embarrassing adolescences.
（貝木）
将来を棒に振るなとか
みんな 恥ずかしい青春を
送ってきたとか
After a while, everything will be a good memory.
しばらくすれば
いい思い出になるとか
Stuff like that... Obvious things that adults tell children.
そういう 大人が子供に言うような
当たり前のことを言ったんだ
So if asked what I did...
だから 何をしたかと問われれば
I answer I only did the obvious.
俺は 当たり前のことをしたまでだ
H-Hey!
（阿良々木）お… おい！
Kaiki! What are you doing?
貝木 何してんだ！
Shut up and stay back, Araragi!
（貝木）
うるさいな
引っ込んでろよ 阿良々木
Know your place. There is absolutely nothing that you can do for Sengoku.
わきまえろ
お前が
千石のためにできることなんか
何もないんだから
The talisman that Gaen-senpai entrusted to you... Is this it?
お前が 臥煙先輩から託されていた
という お札は
これか？
Huh? Yeah, it is.
え… ああ そうだけど
I see.
そうか
Here.
ほれ
Don't make a mistake next time you choose to use this on someone.
今度は間違うなよ
これを使うべき相手を
I won't use it... I'll never use something like this.
使わないよ
僕はこんなもの 使わない
H-Hey! Wait! Where are you going, Kaiki!
お… おい 待てよ！
どこに行くんだ 貝木！
どこにも なにも…
Where, you ask? I shouldn't be in this town in the first place.
俺は 本来
この町にいちゃダメなんだよ
If Senjougahara finds out that I'm loitering around here, she'll kill me.
こんな所にいることがバレたら
戦場ヶ原に殺されてしまう
My job is done.
Animation Number 443
Got quite a bit of money.
Make sure to take that girl back home, Araragi.
ちゃんと その子を
家まで送ってやれよ 阿良々木
The Slug Tofu will naturally depart from her in about three days or so...
蛞蝓豆腐は
３日もすれば自然に離れるから
そのあとの心配もしなくていい
...so you don't have to worry about the aftereffects.
どうしても離れないようなら
塩でもかけろ
If it's refusing to part with her, toss some salt on her.
And after that, make sure that you have no part of that girl's life till the day you die.
そして あとは
お前は 一生 その子に
関わらないようにしてやるんだ
いいな？
Got that? Hurry up and become a memory in her mind.
さっさと思い出になってやれ
I can't do something so irresponsible.
（阿良々木）
そんな無責任なこと
できるわけないだろ！
千石が こんな目に遭ったのは
It's my fault that Sengoku ended up this way. I have to take responsibility...
僕のせいなんだから
僕は その責任を…
Don't you get it?
分からないのか？
There is nothing you can do for that girl.
お前は その娘のために
何をしてやることもできないんだよ
If you're around, that girl will just be useless.
お前がいたら
その娘はダメになるだけだ
Romance can strengthen people, but it can also make them useless.
恋は人を強くすることもあれば
人をダメにすることもある
Because you were with her, Senjougahara was able to strengthen herself a bit.
戦場ヶ原は お前がいたから
多少は強くなったんだろう
But Sengoku Nadeko will just be useless if you're with her.
しかし 千石撫子は お前がいたなら
ダメになるだけだ
（阿良々木）あ…
Senjougahara became useless because she was with me.
（貝木）
戦場ヶ原は
俺がいたからダメになった
You came in and strengthened her.
それを お前が強くした
So this time I was the right guy for the situation, you could say.
ま… だから 今回は
適材適所というか
Something like repaying that old favor.
その借りを
返してやったみたいなもんだ
Kaiki...
貝木
Would Sengoku become happy if I wasn't around?
千石は 僕がいなければ
幸せになれるんだろうか？
Who knows? She seemed very happy up until moments ago...
（貝木）さあな
さっきまで 幸せだったみたいだが
But then, becoming happy isn't the primary objective of human life.
別に 幸せになることが
人間の生きる目的じゃあないからな
It doesn't matter if she's happy or not as long as she can become what she wants to be.
幸せになれなくとも
なりたいもんに
なれりゃいいんだし
But in any case, if she keeps on living, maybe something good will happen in due time.
けど ま… 何にしても
生きてりゃ そのうち
いいこと あるんじゃねえのかよ？
Well then, I'll see you again.
じゃあ また会おう
Animation Number 459
Well, I did the minimum amount of fudging the story, so I'm going to leave you to clean it up.
（貝木）
まあ 最低限の ごまかしは
しておいてやったから
後始末は任せるよ
Old soldiers only fade away. What remains is for the children's generation.
老兵は ただ去るのみ
あとは子供たちの時代だ
After creating a huge mess, don't try to show off for no reason...
（戦場ヶ原）
めちゃくちゃにしておいて
意味もなく 格好つけないで
And still, at the end,
Animation Number 459
Thank you very much. You saved me.
ありがとうございます
助かりました
that's what she said again.
Animation Number 461
Then, this is goodbye.
じゃあ これで お別れね
（貝木）そうだな
Right. I'm done with you now. It's the end.
これで お前とは終わり
ジ･エンドだ
Bye-bye.
（貝木）それじゃ
See ya.
Hey, Kaiki. Can I ask one thing?
（戦場ヶ原）
ねえ 貝木 １つ いいかしら？
You can't.
ダメだ
About two years ago, did you really think I was in love with you?
（戦場ヶ原）
２年前のことなんだけれど
あなた 本当に
私が あなたのことを
好きだったと思っている？
Like I freaking care.
Animation Number 461-2
At least I thought you did.
（貝木）俺は そう思っていたな
（戦場ヶ原）
そう
I see... Then I deceived you just to my liking.
それは
いいように だまされたわね
私に
I guess. So, what of it?
（貝木）そうだな
で それが どうした？
（戦場ヶ原）
いいえ それだけだわ
No, that's all.
From here on, be careful of bad women.
これからは 悪い女には
気をつけなさい
Right.
（貝木）そうだな
お前は
手紙を出すときには
And you, make sure you don't forget to sign the letters that you send.
署名を忘れないように
気をつけろ
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
It's really not much.
（貝木）
なんのことはない
ホテルの部屋に
差し込まれていた
The fact that Senjougahara Hitagi was the author of that letter that was slid into my hotel room...
あの手紙の差出主が
戦場ヶ原ひたぎである
ことなど
...wasn't something worth complimenting even if I saw through it.
見抜いたところで
褒められるものではない
—It wasn't hard to figure out,
Animation Number 471
but it took some time.
Then why, after being the one to make the request, would she say something so contradictory as "pull out"?
では どうして 自分で
依頼しておきながら
自分で手を引けなんて
矛盾したことを
言ってきたかといえば
That is because she knows me very well.
それは あいつが
俺のことを
よく知っているからだ
It's because Senjougahara Hitagi knows very well that my personality won't want to pull out if told to.
手を引けと言われれば
手を引きたく
なくなってしまう
俺の性格を
戦場ヶ原ひたぎは
よく知っているからだ
But...
しかし
Senjougahara aside, how calculating was Gaen-senpai in all of this?
（貝木）
戦場ヶ原は ともかく
臥煙先輩のほうは
本当は どこまで
計算ずく
だったのだろうか？
Since she knows, even more than Senjougahara,
手を引けと言われれば
手を引きたくなくなる
俺の性格を
that my personality won't want to pull out if told to.
戦場ヶ原以上に
あの人は
知っているのだから
In truth, perhaps she only paid me the huge sum of three million yen...
ひょっとして
300万円という大金を
俺に対して支払ったのは
...because she intended to help me financially with this job?
単なる資金援助という
もくろみが
あったのではないだろうか？
Maybe I was cleverly manipulated by that woman... By that senpai...
俺は あの女に あの先輩に
いいように
踊らされただけではないのか
But still, I think...
それにしても と思う
What the hell is Oshino doing now of all times?
しかし 忍野(おしの)のヤツは こんなときに
一体 何をしているのだろうか？
That good-natured man who wants to show off in front of kids hasn't shown up...
あの お人よしが
子供の前では
格好つけたがる あの男が
Can such a thing really happen?
姿を現さないなんてことが
果たして あるだろうか？
Where the hell is he now, and what the hell is he doing there?
あいつは 一体
今 どこで 何をしているのだ？
ハア ハア ハア…
I-It's just like Ougi-san said.
（中学生）
お… 扇さんの言ったとおりだった
本当に帰ってきていたんだ
この詐欺師…
You really were back. You con artist...
お… お前のせいで
お前のせいで お前のせいで…
Because of you...
Because of you... Because of you!
I see. He's one of the many junior high kids whom I deceived last time I was in this town.
（貝木）
そうだ
前に 俺が
この町に来たときに だました
大量の中学生のうちの１人だ
What's with this kid? Did he get inflicted with a reversed curse?
なんだ？　こいつ
呪い返しにでもあったのか？
Then, this junior high kid is...
ならば この中学生が…
Maybe he's the root of all evil... The junior high kid who enchanted Sengoku with the "charm."
事の発端である
千石に おまじないを仕掛けた
中学生なのかもしれない
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Come to think of it, I resolved the letter issue...
そういえば 尾行者のほうの正体は
...but the shadower's identity wasn't exactly resolved yet.
厳密には いまだ
不明のままだったな
I thought it could perhaps have been Senjougahara or Gaen's observer,
Animation Number 505
but if this was the outcome that Gaen had hoped for,
there would be no meaning to this.
Animation Number 505
Then, was this junior high kid the shadower?
ならば 尾行者は
この中学生だったのか？
No, it wasn't him.
いや 違う
I judge with a bloodied head.
Animation Number 507
I can't think that he has enough sanity to shadow someone else.
人を尾行できるような正気が
こいつに あるとは思えない
Wait, didn't he mention some person's name just now?
そういえば さっき
誰か 人名を言っていなかったか？
Ougi? Who is that?
扇？
誰だ？　それは
It was a name that I felt I had heard somewhere before, but I could no longer think anymore.
どこかで 聞いたような気もする
名前だったが
俺は それ以上
考えることはできなかった
（中学生）う… わあ〜！
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
They say money talks even in hell.
（貝木）
地獄の沙汰も金次第という
Since I don't have money saved up, I felt really glad from the bottom of my heart...
貯金のない俺だから
最後に
いくらか小銭を稼いでおいて
...that I was able to earn a bit of pocket change at the very end.
本当に よかったと
心から思った
Preview
Dialogue Script - Nisio Isin
4-Koma Illustrations - Haritama Hiroki
Preview
（火憐）
火憐だぜ！
Karen here!
And Tsukihi!
（月火(つきひ)）
月火だよ！
I'm Tsukihi!
We're the Fire Sisters!!
Love!
（２人）
２人合わせて
ファイヤーシスターズ！
Together, we're the Fire Sisters!
Ah! It's Kanbaru-senpai!
Makya Makya
（月火）
いや〜 終わったね
Ah, it's over. Well then, shall we visit Nadeko-chan?
さあ 撫子ちゃんの
お見舞いに行くか！
（火憐）
メンタル 強すぎるだろ
You're completely mental.
（月火）
物語シリーズ
セカンドシーズンも
And they lived happily ever after. With that Monogatari Series Second Season is complete.
Eh! You want to be the main character of the series?
Makya!
これにて おしまい
めでたし めでたし
（火憐）
いや〜
それが まだ続くんだよ
Nope, there is something more.
（月火）
なに？　そうなの？
聞いてないよ
What? Are you sure? I'm not aware of it.
（火憐）
聞いてなかった
だけだろ？
You just didn't listen. Anway, last Preview Quiz!
I might be able to grant that wish...
For real?
とはいえ
最後の予告編クイズ！
（月火）
だから クイズなんて
してないっての！
It's not even a quiz!
（火憐）
恋物語に続く
After the Koimonogatari chapter, who's gonna be the main character of the sixth one?
物語シリーズ
セカンドシーズン
第６フェイズの主役は
What do you think...?
Let's see... The title would be...
（火憐）誰でしょう？
（月火）私！
Me!
（火憐）
神原先生に
決まってんだろうが
IT'S OBVIOUSLY KANBARU-SENSEI, YOU IDIOT!
ぶっ殺すぞ！
（月火）
お姉ちゃんに
ぶっ殺すって言われた
Now Karen-chan wants to beat me to death.
Next time! Monogatari Series Second Season +α, Hanamonogatari Episode 1!
Next Time
Suruga Devil Part 1
（２人）
次回 物語シリーズ
セカンドシーズン＋α
「花物語 第１話
するがデビル 其ノ壱(そのいち)」
Suruga Devil, Part 1.
Kanbaru Suruga Main
"Hanamonogatari"
2014 Production!
Kangusu!
No, it's only Kanbaru.